the C major scale for beginners is the
most common scale to learn first in this
video I'm going to show you exactly how
to play C major scale on piano in the
right hand going up and down one octave
you need to do that before trying to or
more octaves and then once you're done
with this come back and check out parts
2 & 3 which will cover the left hand and
then putting hands together this
channels your guide through developing
all the different skills and knowledge
you need to become a better piano player
and musician so if that's something you
want to do consider clicking the
subscribe button and the notification
browser so you don't miss out on
anything you need to learn just quickly
if this is the first time you've touched
a piano I recommend doing a couple of
other things before trying a scale
learning to name the white notes and I
have a video up on that you can watch
plus you need to get a bit of basic
technique going first how to hold your
hand and start to move your fingers up
and down and I've got a video that will
help you out with that too both of those
are linked in the description below I
also have a worksheet which has all 12
major scales on graphics and finger
numbers for one and two octaves and is
also a link for that in the description
too as this is the first time playing a
scale you really want to listen
carefully to all the steps and follow
them right to the end of the video and
that's going to help you learn more
effectively and get more out of learning
scales that will help you become a
better musician rather than just
learning how to play a scale and at the
end I have some extra tips and some
common things that go wrong that you
want to avoid I've taught a lot of
beginners and send people do these
things and remember a scale is really a
tool to help us play better so you
really want to start off learning to do
things the right way and avoid mistakes
that are going to affect your playing so
the C major scale is named that because
the note C is where we start and major
means the type of scale it is it's the
pattern that we make from that note the
note C we call the root in this case and
it sounds like home it sounds complete
if we land on it we can start a major
scale by playing the same pattern
starting from any of the other notes too
I'll cover how a major scale works
properly in another video so starting on
C and this one here's middle C we'll do
one octave which just means spanning
eight notes the seven notes in the scale
and then we play the C again at the top
making eight and the C major scale is
just all these white notes so no black
notes if we number the notes
gonna help us know where we are in the
scale which is a really really important
thing to do when you're learning music
anyway so 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 and then you
can't call that 8 or often 1 again
sometimes these are called scale degrees
so a fundamental piano skill is to use
finger blocks where we can't reach
everything in one hand position or
there's more notes than you have fingers
the scale will help you start learning
how to divide something up cleverly into
finger blocks and to move through them
smoothly without getting your fingers
all jammed up and confused which is
something that beginners often do so
we're going to go through three steps
here getting them into finger blocks
breaking the notes up and then
connecting the finger blocks smoothly
just a quick reminder of finger numbers
which makes this a lot easier thumbs are
one and then we go outwards two three
four five the important thing here is
that I'm trying to get you to see a
group of notes in one go and not think
step by step too much because chunking
information like that helps out you're
playing loads in the long run so take
fingers 1 2 3 and play the first 3 notes
of the scale together that's the first
block so from there you're gonna lift up
your arm move it across and then play
the next four notes of the scale with
fingers 1 2 4 this is your next block so
that's notes 4 5 6 & 7 at the scale and
then your 5th finger you're just gonna
use on its own for the top note now I
realize you could just add that 4 and a
5 and call that a block of 5 instead but
I'm sort of playing the long game here
because when you eventually do two or
more octaves you only ever use your 5th
finger when you reach the top so the
first thing to get comfortable with
doing might seem a bit silly and
pointless to start with but it'll make
sense when we get to the next step
remember what we're trying to do is get
those blocks of notes and seeing them in
one go and how to mold a block of
fingers into them straight away stuck in
your head clearly go up and down like
this keep repeating it and as you're
doing it make sure to lift your arm up
and float over the top you've got to
control the weight of your arm
making sure you're sitting up straight
over the top of the keys to help to when
you push the notes down don't dig your
weight too hard into the keys or push
any more than you need you just drop
your weight down just the right amount
and then that way when you lift up they
all release nice and comfortably don't
go too fast when it feels solid and you
can see everything clearly your fingers
fall into place you don't accidentally
land in the wrong finger block or
anything like that then move on to step
instead of hitting all the notes in a
block together now we're going to break
them up but at the moment we can pause
and move to the next block connecting
them smoothly is step 3 remember to
check out the video in the description
for something more detailed on basic
technique but as you're doing this what
you're after is a nice clean sound
between the notes as opposed to
crunching any notes together which might
be what you do by accident so as opposed
to here's how you can learn to avoid it
playing involves a joint effort between
your fingers and your arm and really the
rest of your body in some ways too so
start by making sure your arm is held
over the keys properly you should be
able to float around the keyboard like
that so touching the keys but without
pushing them down that means you're
controlling the weight of your arm
you're holding it up and then as you're
pushing down a key you want to feel a
slight movement in your arm going up and
down controlling it and then a little
bit of a push from your fingers but it's
a lot like your arm is directing the
weight through your fingers to the key
play with just this part of your
fingertip so your hand wants to have
this nice curved position with curved
fingers not too flat like that or up too
high and straight putting all this
together means that when you go from
note to note your arm can come up before
going down to the next note which
releases the previous key and gives you
that cleaner sound otherwise when you
dig in that's when you get that stuck
crunching notes together sound which
also adds tension and makes everything
harder basically your wrist wants to
dangle down so it can relax and you can
move around with more agility and
control so get through the first block
like that then use your arm to move to
the next block it's like your arm is a
crane getting your hand into position
remember will smooth out the turn in
next step now as you land in this
position remember to see the whole block
as one that's why we hit them all
together to start with so you see them
as one and get into position that's
going to allow you to reach all of them
but then you just break them up and then
you can just hit the top one
straightaway this time follow exactly
the same process coming down break them
up get to your farm and then move your
hand into position and do the other
three keeping your hand floating over
the top once you can do that a few times
in a row really comfortably then move on
to step three so now what we're trying
to do is connect those blocks together
and smooth it with a turn really what
we're doing is we're tucking our thumb
under as we move our wrist across and
the way to do that effectively is to
when you get to this third note when
you're in this position if you still
maintain everything I've been saying
about holding your hand above the keys
and controlling the weight so your hand
is free to float and relax if you're
just holding this note down with your
fingertip you should be able to just
move around like that comfortably that's
how it wants to feel and then when you
can do that you can just move your wrist
across and at the same time tuck your
thumb like this and then you can reach
the F the fourth note and then when you
push that down if your hand is super
relaxed again your fingers to just kind
of fall over the top like this so one
smooth motion you can practice that just
that specific bit on its own if you like
one extra tip is to not play the white
notes too close to the edge if you do
that and then you tuck your thumb you
can't reach the next one if it's forward
then when you tuck under you can
comfortably reach the next note and
bring your fingers over so what you
don't want to do is twist like this
which is what a lot of people do because
that's gonna really hold you back in the
long run and it's going to make the
playing feel awkward and it's going to
lose the timing so one thing you want to
be doing is learning to think ahead a
little bit so as you are playing this
right hand you need to be thinking about
that thumb turn right on the first note
that way you can almost start leaning
into it on the way up instead
getting to the third note and then
pausing and doing it that will cause a
pause and that will cause a twist in the
wrist whereas if you just sort of lean
into it a bit it all flows together much
more smoothly in your head be thinking 1
2 3 thumb so fingers 1 2 3 relaxed thumb
the real trick is to keep your wrist up
and relax on the way down when you get
to your thumb your thumb is a good
finger to turn over from so when you get
to it here's how I want to think about
this this is going to set you up to
approach fingering in piano much better
in the long run when you're coming up
with your own finger numbers when you
look at the block of three notes that's
coming up next you need to be thinking
I'm going to apply a block of three
fingers to that block of three notes so
you've got these three here and they fit
perfectly in there because it makes
sense for you to end up back where you
started because repeating finger
patterns is also an important skill try
and think of it as you're coming down
thinking ahead is also another important
skill pianists need to have so as you're
coming down be thinking already I'm
going to turn my third finger over and
everything I said about going up applies
to coming down keeping it relaxed and
that way you're free to be agile and
move around on that thumb if you dig too
much weight in you're gonna get stuck
and probably put the wrong finger over
and lose the timing when you get to the
top don't hit the top note again before
you come back down so come straight back
down like that and then when you go back
up same at the bottom don't hit the
bottom note twice just go straight back
up so some tips for playing this don't
skip fingers feel them going in order
sometimes people might go through the
one two finger three that'll throw the
pattern out of whack and you'll end up
running out of fingers before you get to
the top a really common thing that
people do is when you're going up
towards the weaker fingers towards
fingers four and five like there's
people dip their wrist and the other
fingers come up like that it's because
you're pushing too hard with your
fingers and it means you're not
controlling your arm weight going
pan down like that the number one thing
you need to do here is to not practice
these too fast your brain needs those
extra few milliseconds to think about
what it's doing next it's really
important so be really strict with
yourself about that because lots of
people tend to have one or two slow gos
and then they find themselves speeding
up without even realizing they're doing
it so if you're learning by yourself in
particular you need to be really good at
noticing when you're doing that by
accident another thing people sometimes
do is when they make the turn they stick
elbows out so try and avoid that
remember use your shoulder to crane your
arm across like that and don't feel like
you're resting or balancing any weight
on any of your fingers as you're going
across I keep saying it but your arm
needs to feel like it's holding itself
up so you can float over the top try and
keep the timing as even as possible so
prioritize that in your head so don't be
tempted to go it's what people do is
they double check and they triple check
they're going to get it right but at
some point you need to kind of just
commit to it and prioritize making the
next beat on time and going for it don't
forget to have that worksheet linked in
the description with graphics and finger
numbers for all 12 major scales come
back for parts two and three on the left
hand and then putting them together
which should be on the screen when it's
up please leave a like and let me know
in the comments if the video is helpful
and subscribe for more content to help
you develop your piano playing thanks
for watching